Inventory of the Ekaterina Erastovna Zborovskai͡a letters received
Hoover Institution Archives
Ekaterina Erastovna Zborovskai͡a letters received
1917-1918
2000C3
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Letters by the Grand Duchesses Ol'ga, Tati͡ana, Marii͡a and Anastasii͡a relating to conditions of the Russian imperial family in captivity following the Russian Revolution. Includes English translations. Digital copies also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Zborovskai͡a, Ekaterina Erastovna.
Tati͡ana Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess, daughter of Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1897-1918.
Marii͡a Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess, daughter of Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1899-1918.
Anastasii͡a Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess, daughter of Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1901-1918.
Olʹga Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess, daughter of Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1895-1918.
Access
Box 1 may not be used without permission of the Archivist. Use copies available in Box 2; digital copies also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
Friend of the Russian imperial family.
Scope and Content of Collection
Letters by the Grand Duchesses Ol'ga, Tati͡ana, Marii͡a and Anastasii͡a relating to conditions of the Russian imperial family in captivity following the Russian Revolution. Includes English translations.
Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Romanov, House of.
- Letters from Anastasii͡a Nikolaevna (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Letters to Ekaterina Erastovna Zborovskai͡a describing the life of the Imperial family in Tsarskoe Selo.
  - 1917 April 12
  - 1917 April 30
  - 1917 May 20
  - 1917 May 30
- Postcard from Tati͡ana Nikolaevna, 1917 June 5 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Postcard to Ekaterina Erastovna Zborovskai͡a describing the life of the Imperial family in Tsarskoe Selo.
  Rough translation into English: T[sarskoe] S[elo] 1917. 5 July Sweet Katia, one more time, thank you for your letter. Bad weather set in again and it has been raining lately; it is boring for us, but helpful for wheat and other stuff. I always think of you all. You and your Mom are certainly lost without Vitia and Gr[igorii?]. Pass on my regards to them when you write [to them]. I kiss you many times. T[atiana]
- Letter from Marii͡a Nikolaevna, 1917 June 8-9 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Letters from Anastasii͡a Nikolaevna (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - 1917 June 11
  - Postcard, 1917 June 25
    Postcard to Ekaterina Erastovna Zborovskai͡a describing the life of the Imperial family in Tsarskoe Selo with brief notes added by three other sisters. Includes a photograph depicting grand duchesses Anastasii͡a Nikolaevna, Ol'ga Nikolaevna, Marii͡a Nikolaevna, and Tati͡ana Nikolaevna.
    Rough translation into English: 25 June 1917 To A.A. (?)
    Hearty thanks for your nice letter that made me so happy. We also remember everything, and we are constantly talking about that time. Our whole day is strictly scheduled, so the time is passing quickly. – Do you remember August 24 on board the "Dneper" and July 11?!… – We go for walks every day, water our kitchen-garden, and usually pour water on ourselves, because it is so hot, and my brother also pumps water on us! –How is your family doing? I am sitting on a window[-sill] and writing to you. – I am going to classes now – not much fun!. But this is the reason why I have to stop writing. I wish you all-all the best. May the Lord be with you. We remember you always. A[nastasiia]
    I am sending my most hearty wishes and regards. O[lga]
    I remember you and I think of you often. My best regards. M[aria]
    I wish you the best, I am sending my hearty regards. T[atiana]
  - 1917 June 26
  - 1917 July 4
  - 1917 July 10
  - 1917 July 12
- Letters from Marii͡a Nikolaevna (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - 1917 July 12
  - 1917 July 20
    Includes a brief note by Grand Duchess Anastasii︠a︡ Nikolaevna.
- Letters from Anastasii͡a Nikolaevna (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - 1917 July 25
  - 1917 July 31
- Letters from Anastasii͡a Nikolaevna (Box-folder 1: 2)
  Letters to Ekaterina Erastovna Zborovskai͡a describing the life of the Imperial family in exile in Tobol'sk.
  - Postcard, 1917 August 8
    Rough translation into English: 8 August 1917. Tobolsk. Dear Katia! I am writing to you on board the ship. We arrived safely on August 6. We have not moved yet, because the house is not ready for us. A lot of funny things have happened!…Everybody is in good health. The weather is chilly; it is raining now and then. Kind regards to everybody from us. Our letter certainly will not reach you soon. This is sad.
    Best wishes. I kiss you warmly.
  - 1917 August 15
  - 1917 September 20
  - 1917 October 8
  - Postcard, 1917 October 15
    Rough translation into English: Tobol’sk 15 October. V.E.
    We all send our warmest regards and hearty congratulations on your birthday and on your nameday. We think and talk of you constantly. Here [on the picture on the face of the postcard] is the space where we walk. We [often] sit on this balcony; it is very nice. One of the windows that is looking to this side is of Papa’s office. Our windows look to the other side; there is a street there. In general, we live not too badly. The weather is cold these days. There is some snow, but not much. We study every day. We often think of sweet big [… …]. We have just come back from our stroll, and we are sitting all together now. My kind and warm regards to everybody and to Vlad[imir]. I wish you all the best. My warmest regards to you. May the Lord be with you.
  - 1917 November 14
- Postcard from Marii͡a Nikolaevna, 1917 November 14 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  Postcard to Ekaterina Erastovna Zborovskai͡a with birthday wishes.
  Rough translation into English: From the bottom of my heart I send my congratulations to you, dear Katia, and wish you to have life full of all nice and beautiful things. I hope you all are in good health. We are often thinking and talking of you; we had much fun and a nice time together. Olga has not received your letter yet; it probably got stuck somewhere. Poor K.G(?) seems to be having a hard time in Ts[arskoe] S[elo]. I kiss you affectionately. How are you brothers and Iuzin doing? We are missing you. May the Lord be with you, darling. Maria
  Tobolsk. 14 November
- Letter from Anastasii͡a Nikolaevna, 1917 November 21 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Letter from Ol'ga Nikolaevna, 1917 November 28 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  Letter to Ekaterina Erastovna Zborovskai͡a describing the life of the Imperial family in exile in Tobol'sk.
- Letters from Anastasii͡a Nikolaevna (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - 1917 November 28
  - 1917 December 5
  - 1917 December 10
  - Postcard, 1917 December 14
    Christmas card to Ekaterina Erastovna Zborovskai͡a, with Christmas wishes added by three other sisters. 14 December 1917 To A. A[?].
    Rough translation into English: "We send you our hearty congratulations on the holidays and New Year. May the Lord give you all the best!… The scenery [on the face of the postcard] presents a view we saw during one of the strolls we made while we were still living on board ship. The weather is very cold but there is not much snow. We often talk about you all!…How are your people doing? We have settled pretty cosy – all four of us together [in one room]. I have to finish [the letter] now. Once again I am sending my best wishes to you. [Anastasia]
    I also send my hearty wishes to have all happy things. O[lga]
    We study a lot, read [books], go for a walk twice a day. Time is passing very quickly. Thank you for the postcard from N.V. I wish you all the best. T[atiana]
    I hope that [your] shoulder does not hurt any more and you feel well. Warm regards. I wish you all the best in the new year. May the Lord protect you. M[aria]
  - 1918 January 9-11
- Letter from Tati͡ana Nikolaevna, 1918 January 11 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Letters from Anastasii͡a Nikolaevna (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - 1918 January 19
  - 1918 January 19
- Letters from Marii͡a Nikolaevna (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - 1918 January 19
  - 1918 January 26
    Includes a picture of their room in Tobol'sk.
- Letters from Anastasii͡a Nikolaevna (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - 1918 February 7
  - 1918 February 22
- Use copies of above letters (Box 2)